三辆车依次为
1979 AC 3000ME，1972 Hillman Avenger Tiger，1961 Hillman Super Minx
翻译
Monica-卡 石佛哥 shan
InX 17 cc
尼斯湖欢迎你们
杰里米 克拉克森
理查德 哈蒙德
不软 梅
时间轴
Monica-卡 RN
校对
Monica-卡  InX Natas 清野 OckRAZOR 李想 RN
大家好
Hello, everybody!
你好
Hello! Hello!
大家好
Hello!
非常感谢大家
Thank you so much.
真热情啊
What a welcome.
大家好 非常感谢
Hello. Thank you, everyone.
欢迎来到The Grand Tour
Welcome to The Grand Tour,
这次我们来到了尼斯湖畔
which this week comes to you from the shores of Loch Ness
在苏格兰
in Scotland!
现在
Now...
就是这样
Exactly.
好了 对于世界上大多数人而言
Now, to most people around the world,
苏格兰只是一堆美景
Scotland is just a bunch of scenery
还有脸上画着颜料的梅尔吉布森
and Mel Gibson with some paint on his face.
指梅尔 吉布森在《勇敢的心》的经典角色
但实际上不止这些
But actually it's a bit more than that.
这里有一张表 记录了在美国发明的
What we have here is a list of all the important things
美国
飞机
所有重要的东西
that were invented in America, OK?
德国发明了这些
This is what the Germans came up with.
德国
汽车
这里是英国的贡献
Then we've got the English contribution.
英国
电脑
再看看法国人做了些什么
And then let's have a look at what France did.
法国
吹风机
就是这样 我没瞎编
That's it. I'm not making that up.
其实还有卷笔刀
Actually and the pencil sharpener.
哦还有卷笔刀
Oh, and the pencil sharpener!
现在我们看看
Now let's have a look at the list of things
苏格兰人发明的东西
that were invented by Scottish people.
这简直是
It's just...!
不可思议 囊括世间万物
It's unbelievable! It's everything!
无烟火药 克隆技术 彩色相片
Cordite. Cloning. Colour photography.
雷管
Percussion cap.
高尔夫 浓缩柠檬汁 数不胜数
Golf, lime cordial. I mean, the list goes on and on.
-别克 -等等
- Buick! - Hang on a minute.
为啥美国海军也算
Why is the US Navy on there?
讲真 那还真是一个苏格兰人发明的
Not joking, that was actually invented by a Scottish person.
-是吗 -BBC也是 英国特种空勤团也是
- Was it? - So was the BBC, so was the SAS.
所有的特种部队都是 我知道为什么
All Special Forces, in fact. And I think I know why.
如果你来自墨西哥法国或者意大利
If you are from Mexico or France or Italy,
早上醒来 拉开窗帘
you wake up in the morning, open the curtains,
天气晴朗 你就想 我要去海滩
it's a lovely day, think, "I'll go to the beach."
在苏格兰你拉开窗帘
In Scotland you open the curtains...
外面又湿又冷
it's damp and cold:
就会想 我要去棚子里造点什么
"I'll go to the shed and I'll invent something."
实际情况就是这样
That's what's going on there.
事实上我很惊讶 英国人
I'm surprised, actually, the English,
从来不说这是不列颠的发明
don't just say that those are British inventions.
对 这是安迪穆雷综合症
Ah, yes, the Andy Murray syndrome.
安迪·穆雷 苏格兰人 目前网球男单世界第一
说实话 这经常发生
Let's be honest, this does happen a lot.
好吧 亚历山大格雷汉姆贝尔
OK. Alexander Graham Bell,
当他在他的小屋里
when he was working away
捣鼓他的胶木电话和电线时
with his Bakelite and his wires in his shed,
他是个苏格兰疯子
he was a Scottish crackpot.
但他发明了电话以后
When he invented the telephone,
他就变成不列颠天才了
he was a British genius!
运动领域也有这种情况
Exactly the same sort of thing happens with sport.
搞赛车的杰基斯图尔特
Motor racing, Jackie Stewart.
三次F1世界冠军
Three times Formula 1 World Champion.
好的 他是英国人
OK, he's British.
吉姆克拉克 两次F1世界冠军 英国人
Jim Clark. Two times Formula 1 World Champion.
大卫库特哈德 苏格兰人
British. David Coulthard... Scottish.
一次总冠军都没拿过
就是这个道理
That's how it works!
-是的 -我们应该向美国观众
- It is, yes. - Maybe we should explain
解释一下发生了什么
to people in America what's going on here.
对的 我来帮你们理清楚
Yeah, exactly. Let me just clear this up for you.
大西洋彼岸的规矩是这样的
This is how it works on this side of the pond.
这是大英帝国 这里是英格兰 我们老家
This is Britain. This bit is England, where we're from.
这是苏格兰 我们现在的位置
This bit's Scotland, where we are now.
这部分是威尔士 在我家旁边
This bit's Wales, which is next to where I live.
很好 规矩很简单
Exactly. The rules are very simple.
如果你是英格兰人
If you're English
当你功成名就的时候
and you become brilliant or do something brilliant,
你还是英格兰人
you remain English.
如果你是苏格兰人或者威尔士人
If you're Scottish or Welsh
一旦你功成名就了
and you do something brilliant,
英格兰就认定你是不列颠人了
the English decide that you are, in fact, British.
英格兰人真是坏透了 不是吗
The English really are appalling, aren't they?!
就是的
They are!
我告诉你们 我喜欢待在苏格兰
I tell you what, I love being in Scotland
因为所有人都直抒胸臆
because everyone here speaks their mind.
没有什么模棱两可
There's no ambiguity.
苏格兰小镇拉克霍尔 他们的欢迎标语
The town of Larkhall in Scotland, their welcome sign,
我们来看
here we go.
欢迎来到
拉克霍尔
ISIS除外
你们这群娘们滚蛋吧
这就是苏格兰
This is Scotland.
不只是说说 他们还付诸行动
It's not just words, either, it's actions.
还记得几年前格拉斯哥机场的
Do you remember that terrorist attack at Glasgow Airport
恐怖袭击吗
a couple of years ago?
有人想自爆 但炸弹没炸
Somebody tried to explode... bomb didn't go off.
他就跑了 但没跑多远
He ran off and he didn't get very far
因为发生了这件事
because this happened.
我狠狠地
踢了恐怖分子
的蛋蛋
甚至撕裂了
我的脚筋
苏格兰人的处世方式
The Scottish way. That is the Scottish way.
还有
And um...
有趣的是 自此苏格兰再也没有恐怖袭击了
Interestingly, there have been no terrorist attacks in Scotland since.
好好想一想
Just thinking about that for a second.
当他踢他的时候 他的脚一定是撞断
When he kicked him, he must have broken his foot
在另一个人的骨盆上了
on the other guy's pelvis.
-是啊 -这说明那人的蛋蛋
- Yeah. - Which means the guy's plums
就在冲击的中心区域
were in the middle of the impact.
当恐怖分子那天早上醒来时
When that terrorist woke up that morning,
他肯定想 好吧
he must've thought, "Right,
今天我将遇到的最糟糕的事
"The worst thing that'll happen to me today
就是我要炸了
is I'm gonna blow up."
这并不是最糟的 不是吗
It wasn't, though, was it?
因为唯一爆掉的东西是他的蛋蛋
Cos the only thing to explode was his knackers.
-我们能继续了吗 -好主意
- Can we get on with the show? - Yes. Good idea.
因为在今晚的汽车节目中
Because in tonight's car programme...
我在发动机上尿尿
I urinate on an engine...
理查德穿了件滑雪衫
Richard wears an anorak...
船长磕了药
and James takes drugs.
但首先 我想聊一下菲亚特
But first, I want to talk about Fiat.
现在最有名的是菲亚特500
They're mostly known these days for the 500,
一辆复古的小掀背车
which is a small retro hatchback.
但是缺席了数十年后
But after an absence of more than a decade,
他们又回到了赛车场上
they are back in the sports car game.
所以我去了埃博拉症赛道
So I went down to the Eboladrome
看看他们拿出了什么
to check out what they've come up with.
就是它了 对比下500
Here it is. And as with the 500,
你可以立马看出
you can tell straightaway
菲亚特打了怀旧牌
that Fiat are playing the nostalgia card
因为这辆车叫做124 Spider
because this car is called the 124 Spider,
向70年代的后驱双座跑车致敬
in honour of their rear-wheel drive roadster from the '70s.
然而在外表之下
Under the skin, though,
124基于全新的马自达MX-5
the 124 is based on the thoroughly modern Mazda MX-5.
菲亚特提供了一些重要的部件 例如引擎
Fiat supply some important things like the engine
还有车身
and the body,
但这两辆车都是
but both cars are built
在日本的同一生产线上制造的
on the same production line in Japan.
从表面上看 没有什么问题
On the surface, that is no bad thing.
你晚上能睡得更安稳
You're gonna sleep a lot better at night
因为知道你的意大利车
knowing that your Italian car
实际上是日本人组装的
was actually put together by the Japanese.
但这也产生了一个问题
However, it does raise a question.
这是菲亚特自己的跑车
Is that a sports car in its own right,
还是一辆贴牌的马自达
or just a Mazda with a different badge on?
好的 在我们探寻之前
Well, before we find out,
让我们近距离看一下这个标志
let's look a bit more closely at the badge.
因为你会注意到 上面写着阿巴斯
Because you'll notice it says Abarth.
当菲亚特想要在车底点一把火的时候
Abarth are Fiat's go-to people
阿巴斯就是他们的关键人物
when they want to light a fire under one of their cars.
不是真点一把火 而是在已有的基础上
Not light an actual fire, but give what's already there
添加一些热情 活力 还有火
some extra zest and zing and fire.
首先 阿巴斯调校了1.4升涡轮增压发动机
For starters, Abarth has tuned the 1.4 litre turbo-charged engine,
所以这最火热的124 比任何MX-5都快
so that this, the hottest 124, is faster than any MX- 5.
百公里加速6.8秒
0- 60 takes 6.8 seconds.
最高时速233公里
And the top speed is 145mph.
但在这样的车里感觉时速有233百万
But in a car like this that feels like 145 million.
对我而言肯定够了
Certainly bundles for me.
124不仅是性能上远远超过了
And it's not just performance where the 124 has the edge
他同父异母的日本兄弟
over its Japanese half-brother.
我必须承认 这还是一个
I have to admit, and this comes from someone
在MX-5上挑不出毛病的人说的
who struggles to find fault with the MX-5,
124的声音更棒
the 124 does sound better.
阿巴斯安装了 Record Monza 排气系统
Abarth have given it something called the Record Monza exhaust system.
它能让小车发出大车的噪声
What it does is make a small car produce a big-car noise.
就像披着狮子皮的猫
It's like a cat in a lion suit
这就是你想要的戏剧效果
and that's exactly the sort of panto you want.
我想说的是 这车我行我素
What I'm saying here is that this car does its own thing.
它有自己的个性 那很重要
It has its own personality. And that's important.
但接下来的一点 可是124的软肋
But on the next point, the 124 does take a bit of a body blow.
你看 这辆阿巴斯很贵
You see, there's a price to pay for all this Abarth-ness.
价格是30000英镑
And that price is ￡30,000.
比顶配MX-5要多5000英镑
￡5,000 more than the top MX-5.
不过 124在皮囊之下给的东西更多
That said, the 124 does give you more under the skin,
特别是在操控系统上
most notably in the handling department.
阿巴斯给车配备了一个限滑差速器
The thing is, Abarth have given this car a limited-slip diff...
这让漂移变得信手拈来
which makes sliding something you command.
MX-5可没有这个
The MX-5 doesn't have that.
也没有这个运动模式按钮
Neither does it have this sport button here,
它能将稳定控制系统放开
which relaxes the stability control.
放得非常开
Quite a lot.
所以 我们有一辆很快的车
So, what we have here is a car that's fast,
它声浪迷人 过弯富有乐趣
sounds good and is great fun in the corners.
但还有更重要的一点
But there's something else very important about the 124.
我不知道它和MX-5是不是真的
I don't know that there's really a million miles of difference
差了十万八千里
between this and the MX-5.
但当我开这车时 我开的是辆意大利跑车
But everything I do in this car I'm doing in an Italian sports car.
这不可能让你提不起兴致
And it is impossible for that not to put you in a good mood.
再次坐进一辆意大利双座小跑车的感觉真好
It does feel so good to be in a small, Italian roadster again.
也该是时候了
It's about time.
这辆小菲亚特就是要搅动你的情绪
Everything about this little Fiat is designed to stir the emotions.
让你笑得像个孩子
And make you smile like a child.
直至这个黑色复古引擎盖
Right down to the retro black bonnet.
天呐 我爱黑色的引擎盖
God, I love a black bonnet!
这实在是
It just... Ooh!
这简直是 一个黑色的引擎盖
It's just...a black bonnet.
只有酷的车才有黑色前盖 真的
Only cool cars have black bonnets. Fact!
我很喜欢MX-5
I really like the MX-5.
但124在日式的基础上
But the 124 has taken those Japanese foundations
又加入了些意式的表演技巧
and added some Italian showmanship.
所以比起马自达我更想要这个
That's why I'd have it over the Mazda.
我不只是喜欢它 我爱它
I don't just like it, I love it.
这很有趣 因为
It's interesting that, because...
你知道 我热衷于意大利跑车
..as you know, I'm a sucker for an Italian sports car.
爱之入骨 尤其是阿尔法
Love'em to bits especially the Alfa.
然而 我开过普通版的124
However, I've driven an ordinary, cooking Fiat 124
没有MX-5那么好 难以望其项背
and that is not as good as an MX-5, not even close.
对的 你还是不要MX-5了
That's true. You'd be better off with the MX-5.
除非你想要最快的MX-5
Unless you want the fastest MX-5,
也就是买一辆阿巴斯
in which case buy the Abarth.
-很有道理 -我们是不是给了消费者建议
- Quite. - Have we just done consumer advice?
有一点 我们快速过
A little bit. A little bit. Moving on quickly.
对 我们继续 我们来看看
Yes, we will, move it on. And we'll find out
阿巴斯在埃博拉症赛道上能跑多快
how fast the Abarth goes round the Eboladrome.
当然了 那就意味着将他交给
That, of course, means handing it over to a man
一个认为胡子是列宁发明的人
who thinks that beards were invented by Lenin.
没错 就是老美
Yep. It's the American.
他来了 从容不迫 蓄势待发
There he is, poised and ready.
他出发了
And he's off.
轮胎轻微打滑
With a skitter of wheelspin
排气声圆滑悦耳
and a fruity noise from the exhaust.
直接进入湿漉漉的不直道
Straight onto a soaking-wet Isn't Strait.
我的生活...
What the hell...
到底经历了什么...
has happened in my life...
我才会在湿乎乎的英国...
that I'm over here driving a Fiat...
开一辆菲亚特
in the wet in England?
也许他并不乐在其中 但他的确精于此道
He may not be enjoying it but he is very good at it.
他驾驶着124飞快掠过积水
As he carves the 124 through the standing water,
将这170匹马力发挥得淋漓尽致
making the best use of its 170 horsepower.
通过留你名弯 车身倾斜得很厉害啊
Really leaning on it as he approaches Your Name Here.
真是大胆
That is ballsy.
现在 大脚刹车
Now, heavy on the brakes,
紧凑而快速地通过这个左弯
swoops round this fast left-hander,
极富技巧 优雅又慌乱地转向过度出弯
and exits with a skilful flurry of stylish over-steer.
回到不直道
Back onto the Isn't.
见鬼 我都不知道这车到底是拿来开的
Hell, I don't know whether to drive this thing
还是拿来当漱口杯的
or use it for a spit-cup.
好极了
Charming!
呆子们会觉得
Nerds will note these conditions
Barchetta会更符合这些条件
would be better suited to a Barchetta.
Barchetta 菲亚特老跑车
如果你喜欢这辆车的话
If you like this car,
我打赌你家里肯定有一堆花里胡哨的靠垫
I bet you got a lot of fancy cushions in your house.
是的 因为我们都知道
Yeah, cos as we know,
靠垫当然代表着 我党
cushions are, of course, Communist.
好了 进入老奶房狭窄的弯角
Right, into the tight complex of Old Lady's House.
紧凑而完美的通过了
Keeping it nice and tidy through there.
全油门通过坑坑洼洼的不平路
And now full power for the lumpy, bumpy sprint
来到变电站弯
down to Substation.
前双闪在大脚刹车后开始亮了起来
Front hazards coming on under hard braking.
所有的菲亚特都这样
All Fiats do that for some reason.
进入绵羊坡 反向锁开始工作
Armful of opposite lock into Field Of Sheep.
激情通过 然后冲过终点
More exuberance through there and across the line.
进入留你名弯的方式真的很大胆
It was a ballsy entry into Your Name Here, that was.
现在让我们看看它能在榜上排在哪儿
Anyway...we must now find out where it ends up on the board.
让我们来看看
Let's have a look.
哦天啊 天啊 哈蒙德
Oh, dear. Oh, dear, Hammond.
所以你大力推荐了一辆
So you've recommended what is
被官方证明是世界上最慢的车
officially the slowest car in the world.
实际上 不 只是我们的圈速榜上最慢而已
Well... No, slowest car on our board.
-我们的圈速榜就是世界 -没错
- Our board is the world. - It is.
好吧 不过你看 地是湿的
All right. Look, it was wet.
那个湖也是湿的 还有人在上面开出过320km/h呢
That lake's wet. Someone once did 200mph on that.
John Cobb 于1952年试图打破水上速度记录时丧生
-而且 -我承认 然后他们就死了
- And... - Then they were killed, I admit.
后来多名挑战者也因各种原因丧生
-但是 -安静 安静
- But... - Quite, quite.
让我们继续下一个话题 是时候
Let's move on. It's time now
让我们优雅的航行在
for us to take a gentle cruise
柔和平静的唠嗑街上了
down the velvety smoothness of Conversation Street.
-那真的很疼啊 -没错
- That really hurts. - It did!
只是让你们都清楚这一点
Just to be absolutely clear with you,
那一下真的 真的很疼
that really, really hurt.
对 那本来应该是个假瓶子的
Yeah. It was supposed to be a pretend bottle.
-让我们继续 -我想唠点重要的事
- Let's move it on. - I would like to converse about something important.
为什么车上要有真皮座椅
Why is it that we have leather seats in cars?
因为实际上 这是一种非常糟糕的材料啊
Because in reality it's a terrible material.
光亮亮滑腻腻
It's too shiny and slippery.
不是太热就是太冷 简直垃圾
It's too hot or it's too cold. It's rubbish.
我觉得那是因为我们总觉得
I think it's cos we got hung up on the idea
真皮座椅就象征了豪华
that leather is somehow posh on a car seat.
但以前并不是这样
But it didn't use to be like that.
古时候 富贵的人们会坐在
In the old days, the posh people sat
车后面的真丝座椅上
in the back of the car on cloth seats,
司机坐在前面的真皮座椅上
and it was the chauffeur sitting at the front--
因为皮椅耐磨
they gave him leather because it's hard-wearing.
我这里有一张老车的照片
I've got a picture here of an old car.
他们甚至都没有给他加个车顶挡一下
They didn't even extend the roof to cover him!
只要再长个三英尺就行了啊
Another three feet would have done it.
我觉得他们是故意的
I think that's deliberate.
那是为了让司机记得他是个下人
I think that's to remind him that he's scum!
除了皮子 你们俩想用什么材料做座椅
What would you two like to have instead of leather?
很多东西都能用啊
There's all sorts of things you could use.
你能用针织毛线
You could have cable-knit wool.
那很棒啊 非常温暖舒适 再让我们四下看看
But it's nice, it's cosy. Desperately looking around.
-他的针织衫拿来做座椅就不错 -温暖舒适
- His jumper would make quite a good car seat. - Cosy.
那是尼龙的 绝对是
It's nylon! It is!
再不然就是化纤
Or pleblon. One of the two.
-这是个好主意啊 -好个鬼啊
- It's a good idea. - It isn't a good idea!
或者这个主意怎么样
Or, how's this for an idea?
我就直说吧
Let me just throw it out there.
为什么不找一头奶牛
Why not take a cow,
把它身上的肉变成汉堡和牛排
turn the middle of it into burgers and steaks,
然后与其把皮扔掉
and then, instead of throwing the skin away,
不如来做你们车上的座椅
use it to cover the seats of your car?
因为皮是个很糟糕的材料 根本就不好用啊
Because it's a terrible material and it doesn't work.
那只是因为你们两个
That's only because you two
决定要开始吃素
have decided to be vegetarians.
不 等一下...
Well, no, hang on...
他们真的已经开始吃素了
They have. They actually have.
一天早上他们一起醒来然后决定
They woke up together one morning and went,
让我们不要再吃肉了
"Let's not eat meat any more."
我们没有从同一张床上醒来过
We didn't wake up together one morning.
-搞明白这一点 -这是个很好的解释啊
- Get clear on that. - It's a fine definition.
谜一样的在同一天同一个时候
Mysteriously arrived at the same conclusion
达成了一个共识
pretty much the same day.
不管怎么说 我们还是要吃鸡肉的
Anyway, we still eat chicken.
没错 而且鸡肉属于蔬菜
Yep. Chicken is a vegetable.
-它不是蔬菜 -就是
- It isn't. - It is.
科学的说 鸡确实是蔬菜
Scientifically, chicken is a vegetable.
如果你把鸡头砍掉 它还能到处跑
If you cut a chicken's head off it still runs around.
说的很对
There you go.
那就说明鸡不是有情众生
Thereby proving it's not a sentient being,
它不过是一种高级蔬菜
it's a higher-order vegetable.
很科学的
Scientifically.
好吧 那我们就用鸡皮
OK, we'll make the seats of your cars
来做你们的座椅 事实上这也不是个坏主意
out of chicken skins. Actually, that's not a bad idea.
鸡皮座椅看起来会不会很像一个特大号的阴囊
Wouldn't a chicken-skin seat look like a giant scrotum?
会 这都是你们不吃肉的错
Yes, and that's your fault for not eating meat.
所以让我们继续 好吗
So now let's move on, shall we?
我有点话要说 回到上世纪20年代
I've got something. Back in the 1920s, OK,
苏格兰的一个工厂造了一辆汽车
a Scottish company made a car
他们说 那是一辆给女士设计的车
which they said was for women.
这有一张照片 它叫Galloway
Got a picture of it here. It's called the Galloway.
它凭什么能被称作女性专用
What about that car makes it for women?
他们说这车的方向盘更小
Well, they said it had a smaller-than-usual steering wheel
-还有更可靠的引擎 -噢对 当然了
- and a more reliable engine. - Oh, yeah, of course,
因为男士们可不想要靠谱的引擎 不是吗
because men don't want a reliable engine, do they?
-只有女性想要 -我讨厌靠谱的引擎
- It's only women! - I hate reliable engines.
同时 你还能站着开车
Also, you can drive it standing up,
上世纪20年代的女性就是这么开车的
which is what women did in the 1920s.
这种东西现如今仍在生产
This sort of thing is still going on today
因为我这有一条新闻说的是
because I've got news of one here.
西亚特Mii Cosmopolitan
A car that's been launched
已经开始设计生产了
called the Seat Mii Cosmopolitan.
我们有一张这车的图片 你看
We have a picture of it. There you go.
-你怎么拼Mii -M-I-I
- How do you spell Mii? - M-I-I.
-实际上是Mii-iii -是Mii-iii
- It's Mii-iii. - It is Mii-iii.
我有了一辆Mii-iii
"I've got a Mii-iii."
这辆车是由西亚特
It's been done in collaboration
和《时尚》杂志共同推出
with Cosmopolitan magazine.
专为都市女孩设计
"It's aimed at Cosmo Girl,"it says.
然后 听好了
And, are you ready?
拥有眼线般的大灯
"The headlights have an eyeliner shape."
-并不是  -停车更方便
- No, they don't. -"It's easy to park."
噢是的 因为
Oh, yeah, cos...
我还是喜欢难停的车
I much prefer a car that's hard to park
因为我是个男人
because I'm a man.
我们能说明一下吗
Can we get something clear here? OK?
这种分性别的车太荒唐了
This gender-splitting of cars is ridiculous.
就好像是女性飞机座椅
It's like saying a woman's airline seat
或者是女性火柴 或者女性任何东西
or a woman's matches or a woman's anything.
我能买一盒女性铅笔吗
"Can I buy a box of women's pencils, please?"
就是 我唯一能想到的分性别的东西
Exactly. The only things I can think of that can be split by gender
-就是自行车 因为有前梁 -是啊
- are bicycles, because of the crossbar. - Yeah.
-还有内衣 -有时候是的
- And underwear. - Sometimes, yeah.
说漏嘴了
Overshare?
我说出声了
I said that out...
当时走得急
I left in a hurry.
说实话 我无法理解
Honestly, I just can't understand
为什么人们会觉得有
why people think there's such a thing
-女性汽车和男性汽车这种东西 -荒谬
- as a woman's car and a man's car. - Ridiculous.
你开车的时候又不是
It's not as if you drive cars
用你的老兄或者蜜汁三角区开车
with your old chap or your magic triangle.
这儿还有
And there's um...
-听着 -脑补出图像了
- Listen... - It's a little graphic.
几年前 沃尔沃做了一款概念车
But a few years ago, Volvo did a concept car,
他们还大肆吹捧
and they boasted very loudly
说这辆车所有的东西
that the whole thing had been designed
都是女性设计的
entirely by women.
我这有一张照片
And I've got a picture of it.
这是一辆有鸥翼门 大功率引擎的轿跑车
It's a coupe with gull-wing doors and a massive engine.
2004 Volvo YCC Concept
是个人都这么设计
It's what everyone would do.
我肯定会这么设计的
I would definitely have done that. Exactly.
当涉及到汽车的时候
Men and women are exactly the same
男人和女人完全一样
when it comes to cars. The end.
-正是 -好的 现在
- Exactly. - Right. Now...
你知道特斯拉吗
You know Tesla?
特斯拉认为它是电动车的先驱者
Tesla believes it's pioneering the electric car.
但并不是这样 60年代有个苏格兰公司
But that ain't so. There was a Scottish company back in the '60s
造了一辆电动车
which made an electric car.
-我这有张照片 -哎我去
- I've got a picture of it here. -  Oh, God!
它叫做痞子
It's called The Scamp.
最高时速56公里
It had a top speed of 35mph,
续航里程32公里
a range of 20 miles.
我想说得非常明白
And I want to make it absolutely plain,
那是苏格兰的 不是不列颠的
that's Scottish, not British.
是的 毫无疑问
It is, yes! Very definitely!
那是苏格兰的
That... that is Scottish.
唠嗑可以结束了
We can end the conversation.
现在全世界的人
Now, all over the world,
都在买又大又乏味的车
people, by and large, buy very boring cars.
我昨天遇见一个人 他刚花了8000英镑
I met a man yesterday who'd just spent ￡8,000
买了一辆5年的老福克斯
on a five-year-old Ford Focus.
我就想 你图啥呢
I thought, Why did you do that?
如果你有8000英镑预算
If you've got ￡8,000 to spend,
你为什么不买辆二手玛莎拉蒂呢
why didn't you buy a used Maserati?
我觉得这是因为 人们相信
I think it's because people believe
如果花8000英镑买二手的意大利车
if you buy the used, exotic Italian car for ￡8,000
它肯定不停地坏
it's going to break down all the time.
对 但真的如此吗 为了找到答案
Yes, but will it? To find out,
我们用自己的钱
we actually put our own money on the line,
每人买了一辆二手玛莎拉蒂
and we each went out and bought a second- hand Maserati.
是的 而且我们觉得
Yes, and then we decided that cars this glamorous
这样富有激情又迷人的车不能在英国测试
and this exciting couldn't possibly be tested in Britain.
所以我们决定在欧洲大陆碰头
So we decided to meet up in continental Europe.
法国北部
这是我们选的赛道
This is the race track we selected.
距离加莱只有96公里
It's just 60 miles from Calais,
我一早就到了 心情愉悦
and I arrived bright and early.
这是一台玛莎拉蒂Biturbo
This...is a Maserati Biturbo.
世界上第一台装备双涡轮的车
First car in the world to be fitted with two turbo chargers.
这台车被命名为S系列
And this particular example is the sought-after S model.
而且只跑了38000公里
And it's only done 24,000 miles.
尽管如此 我还是花了7950英镑
And yet despite that, all I paid for it was £7,950.
来得到这台魅力十足 马力强劲的车
So you get all this glamour, all this power,
还有这些车标 而且在英国的价格
all that badge for less than you'd pay in the UK
比一台六年的丰田普锐斯还便宜
for a six-year-old Toyota "Pious"
为什么哈蒙德开了一台福特Cortina
Why has Richard Hammond arrived in a Ford Cortina?
不对 这不是福特 而是另外一台Biturbo
Wait. It isn't a Ford Cortina, it's another Biturbo!
-这是一台430 -不是
- No, this is the 430. - It isn't!
-430 -Biturbo
- It is! - Biturbo.
这不是Biturbo
This isn't a Biturbo.
-明明就是 -那才是Biturbo
- It is! - That's a Biturbo.
哈蒙德
Hammond.
我很遗憾地告诉你
I'm sorry to have to tell you this.
但是Ghibli Racing
But the Ghibli, the Racing,
Karif Shamal 222和430
the Karif, the Shamal, the 222 and the 430,
都是一样的 根本没钱改
they were all the same car. They haven't got any money.
他们只是改了一下尾标
They just changed the name badge on the back.
都是一样的车
These are the same car.
你的很丑 但依然是同样的车
Yours is very ugly, but it's the same car.
我反对
I dispute that.
这并不是丑 而是优雅
This is not ugly, this is elegant.
-这是意大利风格 -才不是呢
- This is Italian style. - It isn't!
这是一台外观很棒的车子 看啊
That is a fabulous-looking car. Let's look at this.
你的车子咋样 这很艳俗 伙计
What have you got? It's a bit gaudy, mate.
你想听听这台宝贝点火的声音么
You wanna hear this baby fire up.
快出来 逃命啊
Get out! Save yourself!
哦也
Yes!
感受一下这动力吧
Feel the power of that!
你看见地上这摊了么
Have you seen all this--
除了油还能是什么
there's no other word for it-- oil?
好吧
Yeah, that...
-好吧 -好吧
- Yeah. - Yeah.
幸运的是
Happily,
在冒出更多的油之前
before any more could flood out,
詹姆斯来了
James arrived.
你见过比这货还丑的车子么
Have you ever seen a more ungainly-looking machine?
这是怎么了 你的车门坏了么
What's the matter? Is your door broken?
没 是我坏了 你能帮我扶一下车门么 谢谢
No, I'm broken. Can you hold the door for me? Thank you.
看啊 这是一台玛莎拉蒂Zagato Spyder
Behold...the Maserati Zagato Spyder.
-只是台Biturbo而已 -是Zagato Spyder
- Biturbo, mate. - Zagato Spyder.
都是Biturbo
All Biturbos.
我想这台车设计于
I think this was designed
公司还属于雪铁龙的时候
when it was owned by Citroen,
当时已经破产了
which was bankrupt at the time.
然后一些美国人
Then there was some guy in America
持有了一些玛莎拉蒂的股份
who had a bit of Maserati.
然后还有意大利政府 或者菲亚特
And then the Italian Government, or Fiat,
都有一点
they all sort of had bits of it.
他们到处叫嚣 看啊 我们造了一辆新车
They ran around going, We made a new car. Look.
基本一样 只是有了个新名字
It was exactly the same, it just had a new name.
不好意思 詹姆斯 我只是想看一下
Excuse me, James. I just want to see just...
你还有双色真皮呐
Oh, you've got two-tone leather.
不过为啥你的是自动挡
But why have you got an automatic?
我的胳膊断了
I've bust my arm.
这就是为什么我下车要这么久
That's why it took a long time to get out.
你的胳膊真的伤了么
Have you really broken your arm?
你伤的哪只胳膊
Which arm have you broken?
这让我杀气腾腾 脾气暴躁
It has made me murderously bad-tempered
还无法容忍你的愚蠢
and intolerant of your fatuousness.
你真的伤到胳膊了么
Have you seriously broken your arm?
真的伤得很严重
It's fractured quite badly.
-别碰 -你怎么伤的
- Don't touch it. - How did you break it?
-我摔了一跤 -这是你买自动挡的原因吗
- I fell over. - That's why you got an automatic?
-是的 -车顶是自动的么
- Yes. - Is that roof electric?
-不是 -这前面有一个按钮
- No. - There's a button on the front.
-这样啊 原来是手动的 -是的
- Oh, right. So it is manual. - Yes.
好吧 我们必须出发了 上车走吧
Anyway, we must get off. Come on, let's drive on.
你能帮我把车顶收回来么
Can you put the roof back up for me?
不能 我才不要
No! I'm not doing that.
我们决定先进行一场直线加速
We decided first of all to have a drag race,
在我们的车和另一类价格相当的车
between our cars and a similarly-priced modern car...
铃木"芹菜"之间进行
the Suzuki Celery.
铃木Celerio
紧张时刻
Tense moment.
糟糕的是 发车直道太窄了
Sadly, however, the pit straight was too narrow
无法容纳四台车
for our four cars.
你弄啥嘞
What are you doing?
哈蒙德你这个白痴
Hammond, you idiot!
-你撞了我的玛莎拉蒂 -你撞了我的
- You crashed into my Maserati! - You crashed into mine!
我无处可去了 那边是护墙
I've got nowhere to go. There's a barrier there.
我也无处可走了 我就在那儿
There was nowhere for me to go. I was where I was.
第二次尝试
So, for the second attempt...
我主动走了维修道
I volunteered to go down the pit lane.
耶 我太聪明了
Yes, this is genius!
不过这也没有成功
And that didn't work, either.
重新回到赛道 哈蒙德在那里
Re-emerging on the track. Hammond is there.
搞什么鬼
What the hell?
糟糕
Oh, shit!
我的天呐
Oh, my God!
为什么我们不能好好跑一场加速赛
Why the hell can't we just do a drag race properly?
能有什么难的
It can't be that difficult.
又经历了一次事故后 我们决定
After this latest accident, we decided that,
由于哈蒙德的车子排量最大
as Hammond's car had the biggest engine...
由他来代表玛莎拉蒂的荣耀出战
he'd represent Maserati's honour on his own.
好吧 就是这样了 我是被选中的车手
OK, this is it. I am the elected driver.
天选之子 自带主角光环
The chosen one. The kingpin.
我很喜欢
I like that.
轮胎溅起了大量的水
Massive amount of bleeping about...
不过
But then...
终于 涡轮开始发力
Finally, it spools up, turbos whizzing away.
绝对碾压
And yes! Absolutely creamed it!
他们选择我实在是太正确了
Yep, they were right to pick me.
还有这台车 玛莎拉蒂 430
And the car, the 430...Maserati.
现在你已经证明了 作为一个团队
Now you've established that, as a team,
我们的双涡轮增压玛莎拉蒂比
our twin turbo-charged Maseratis are faster
67马力的小铃木快多了
than a 67-horsepower Celery,
现在让我们抛开这台小车
let's get rid of the little Japanese car
来看一下我们这三台车里
and find out which of our three cars
哪一个在这条赛道跑的最快
is the fastest round the track.
我们将会驾驶着玛莎拉蒂
We'll be driving Maseratis
狂奔在欧洲大陆的赛道上
on a race track in continental Europe.
听起来很棒不是么
Sounds good, doesn't it?
你怎么了 怎么看起来如此悲惨
What's the matter with you? Why do you look so miserable?
我的胳膊断了
I've broken my arm.
如果我们要跑赛道的话
If we're gonna drive round a track,
至少能给我一个残疾人用的方向盘助力球吗
can I at least have one of those disabled knob things?
-你懂的 -就是方向盘上的那种
- You know. - On the steering wheel?
对 就像叉车上的那样
Yeah, like a forklift truck has.
听起来相当公平啊
Sounds fair enough.
就在我们的同事享受
So, whilst our colleague enjoyed
他的特殊早餐的时候
his special breakfast,
哈蒙德和我安装好了他的助力球
Richard and I attached his steering knob.
走你
There you go.
然后我们驶上了赛道
And then we hit the track.
这台车的起源
The roots of this car,
是1957年的 德国大奖赛
they were planted during the 1957 German Grand Prix.
方吉奥驾驶的那台玛莎拉蒂250F
Fangio, at the wheel of his Maserati 250F,
他在22圈里追上了48秒的差距 赢得了比赛
overcame a 48-second deficit in 22 laps to win the race.
期间十次打破圈速记录
He smashed the lap record ten times.
这样的家族血统是不会轻易消失的
You don't lose a pedigree like that.
走你 感觉尾巴有点躁动
Here we go. Feel the tail kick out a little bit.
或者前面也有点
Or the front go.
还是车尾 又到前面
There's the back. On the front.
天啊 我控制住了
Oh, God. I've got it.
驾驶玛莎拉蒂进行飞驰圈
Flying laps in a Maserati.
这就和斯特灵莫斯做的一样
This is exactly what Stirling Moss did.
Stirling Moss 英国传奇F1车手 与Fangio齐名
并不完全一样 有一点像
Not exactly. Bits of it are.
与此同时 在敞篷车里
Meanwhile, in the convertible,
詹姆斯对于自己的新方向盘旋钮很不满意
James was very unhappy with his new steering knob.
天啊 这是个左手弯
Oh, God, it's the left-hander.
把儿都弯了
Bend the knob.
那两个家伙有什么毛病
What is the matter with those two?
我们很好 我们状态很棒
We're OK. We're in good shape.
不 我们没有
- No, we're not!
尽管我幸运地救回了车
Despite my lucky-dip handling,
我最终还是赶上了哈蒙德
I did eventually catch Hammond.
超他 就在内线超
Take him! Take him on the inside!
耶
Yes!
不要啊
No!
不要啊 我的天啊
No, I... Oh, God, strewth.
他就像要失控了
He's going surely now!
天啊
Jesus!
这台车的马力太大了 加油啊
It just has too many horsepowers here. Come on!
糟糕
Oh, shit.
克拉克森先生的情况有些不妙
Mr Clarkson is indisposed briefly.
过了一会儿 哈蒙德先生也没有幸免
And moments later, so was Mr Hammond.
不要啊
No, no, no!
给点力啊
Come on!
没有得出任何结论之后
So, having learned absolutely nothing at all...
我们决定不跑赛道了
we decided to abandon the race track
而是进行一次1100公里的巡游
and embark on a 700-mile cruise
前往法国南部
to the south of France.
詹姆斯对于这项计划感到很开心
James was very pleased with this plan.
这才像样嘛 不是么
This is more like it, isn't it?
不要在赛道上乱跑
Not mucking around on a race track,
那样的坏主意不适合这些老车
which is always a bad idea in old cars.
我们要进行一次像样的公路旅行
We're going on a proper road trip
去世界上最可爱的地方
to a lovely part of the world
驾驶着令人回味而有异国情调的
in very, very evocative, exotic cars--
玛莎拉蒂
Maserati!
在20世纪70年代 玛莎拉蒂把全部车型都以
In the 1970s, Maserati was naming all its cars
充满异域风情的暖流来命名
after...exotic-sounding warm winds:
比如Mistral Khamsin Bora
Mistral, Khamsin, Bora.
当我在唐卡斯特度过童年时光的时候
When I was a kid growing up in Doncaster,
我就想
I just thought,
我不知道Mistral是啥
I've no idea what a Mistral is
但我就想要一个
but I want one!
玛莎拉蒂  法国南部
Maserati. South of France.
一切都是那么合拍
It just sounds right.
但是很快
However, fairly soon,
现实开始变得
reality began to stick its unwelcome nose
异常残酷
into the equation.
这车没有暖风 我也没办法除雾
You get no heat in here and I can't de-mist at all.
还有刹车
The brakes.
有一边刹车很好
It brakes one wheel very well.
但是每次都只有一边有刹车 还不知道是哪一边
But only one wheel at a time. And you never know which one.
詹姆斯 我的车灯晃到你了么
James, are my lights dazzling you?
有一点 因为我开的是大灯
- Yeah, a bit. - Because they seem to be on main beam,
但我没法调成近光
but I can't dip them.
有趣的是 就算我开远光灯
Interesting thing is,if I put my headlights on full beam,
对向也没人对我闪灯啊
nobody coming the other way flashes at me.
你听到那个响声了么
You hear that rattling?
是方向盘
That's the steering wheel.
除了车子本身的问题外
On top of the mechanical issues,
还有一个问题
there was the problem
就是詹姆斯在右舵车里
of James tackling the toll booths
试图缴过路费
in his right-hand-drive car.
我们还剩1126公里
We've got 700 miles to go.
按这速度 永远都开不到了
It's going to take us for ever at this speed.
雪上加霜的是
And then, to cap it all...
杰里米 你车底火花四射
Jeremy, there are sparks coming from under your car.
我觉得你得停车看看
I think you probably need to stop.
-快看  -什么东西起火了
- Oh, look. - Something's on fire.
-起火啦  -嗯 撒泡尿灭火吧
-Fire!  -Right. Might have to piss on it.
-别啊  -你先回避
- Oh, no! - Go round there!
他肯定会解释这是紧急服务
He's going to claim to be an emergency service now.
可惜 我们的旅程
Annoyingly, our road trip
不如想象的那般入流
wasn't proving to be as stylish as we'd hoped.
在下一个加油点
So, at the next petrol stop,
詹姆斯对我们买的礼物
with James failing to appreciate
欣赏无能
a present we'd bought for him...
你以前幽默感很好的
You used to have a good sense of humour.
你在搞笑的时候 我确实能配合
I do have a good sense of humour when you're being funny.
-但很难得  -我有个新主意
- Which you are sometimes. - ...I suggested a new idea.
听下我的新想法
Listen, listen. I've had a thought.
法国南部太远了
South of France is a long way away.
我们干嘛不去法国北部
So why don't we go to the north of France instead?
-有道理  -好主意
- Yes! - That is a good idea.
比起南部
And there's much more to see and do in the north
北部更好看 更好玩
than there is in the south of France.
北部有什么好看的
What is there to see and do in the north of France?
加莱有个难民营
Well, there's the immigrant camp in Calais.
还有那个烧死女人的广场
There's that square where they set fire to a woman.
指在卢昂的广场烧死圣女贞德
还有呢
Yes.
肯定还有其他玩意儿的
There'll be other stuff. There will be other stuff.
谢谢各位
OK. Thank you very much.
非常感谢
Thank you so much. Thank you.
我们稍后再继续
We'll pick that up later on,
但现在又到了明星脑碰脑环节
but now it's time to play Celebrity Brain Crash!
-依然糟糕  -不忍直视
- Yeah, it's still terrible. - Awful!
好的 对于本周的嘉宾有什么可说的呢
OK, now what can we say about our guest this week?
他是苏格兰人 曾在奥运会上拿过奖牌
He's Scottish, but he won a gold medal at the Olympics.
所以他当然是英国人
So of course he's British.
他最开始是自行车手
He started out in cycling,
后来明智地转向赛车
then very wisely took up motor racing.
曾参加过勒芒
He actually competed at Le Mans.
但今天他要划船进场
But today he's in a boat.
各位 有请克里斯霍伊爵士
Ladies and gentlemen, Sir Chris Hoy!
他来了
There he is!
来了
There he is.
他肯定不会出事
He's gonna be all right.
他划错方向了
He's rowing it the wrong way round.
各位 好消息是
The great thing is, everyone, the great thing is...
尼斯湖是个宁静的内陆湖 没有任何危险
that Loch Ness is a peaceful, inland lake with no hazards at all.
终于有位嘉宾能进棚了
We may finally get a guest to the studio.
太棒了 让他安然无恙的上岸吧
Yeah, that would be great. Get him in unharmed.
-加油啊 霍伊爵士  -加油
- Come on, Sir Hoy! - Come on.
-你可以的  -我天
- Come on, you can do it! - Oh, my...
发生了什么
What happened? How...? What...?
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen...
你们刚才是为霍伊爵士的惨死而鼓掌
you've just applauded the tragic death of Sir Hoy.
他大概是撞上水雷了
No idea. I think he must have hit a mine.
你们也看到了
And there was a terrific explosion,
刚刚惨烈的爆炸
you may have seen it.
他现在已经
And he's now...
他已经去了
Well, he's gone, hasn't he?
所以他来不了吗
Does that mean he's not coming on, then?
詹姆斯 他炸了
Well, James, he's exploded
变成残渣碎屑了
and been reduced to chops and offal.
所以来不了了
So that is a no.
没事 我有后备计划
It's OK. I've got a backup plan.
你知道车载语音系统吧
You know voice activation systems in cars?
通常都用不了
They don't really work,
尤其是在苏格兰
particularly they don't work in Scotland.
接下来是个短片
As we shall now demonstrate with a short clip
有人试图将他的沃克斯豪尔和手机配对
of a man trying to pair his telephone with his Vauxhall.
-陪怼  - 您可以说"配对"
- Pair.  - You can say "pair".
选择设备 反馈 帮助或取消...
Select device. For feedback, help or cancel...
陪怼
Pair.
您可以说"配对"...
You can say "pair".
我特么刚说了陪对
I just (BLEEP) said pair!
...或取消
...or cancel.
陪怼
Pair!
您可以说"配对" 选择设备
You can say "pair". Select device.
反馈 帮助或取消
For feedback, help or cancel...
陪~~对
Pa-a-a-ir.
请再说一次
Pardon.
我最佩服他一点的是
What I really love about this guy
他居然能坚持这么久
is how long he perseveres for.
继续看
Watch this.
陪~~对
Pa-a-a-a-ir.
您想要添加或删除设备吗
Do you want to add or delete a device?
-是的 添加设杯  -请再说一次
- Yes! Add a device. - Pardon?
添加设杯
Add a device.
请使用配对功能和外接设备
Using the pair function and the external device...
小伙子有前途
He was brilliant. Anyway...
这是个大问题
That is the problem. That is the problem,
哈蒙德 但我有解决办法
but, Hammond, I have a solution. OK?
先别吐槽
No, don't scoff. Don't scoff.
这是一个廉价的系统
This is a system that is cheap,
全世界都能用
works anywhere in the world,
不管多老的车
and you can fit it to any car,
都能安装使用
no matter how old it is.
让我演示一下 上车
Let me show you how it works, OK? Step in.
准备好了吗 语音激活系统
Ready? Voice activation.
启动雨刷
Engage wipers.
这就是个人啊
It's just a man!
来自保加利亚的加夫利尔
It's Gavril from Bulgaria.
他无所不能 看 选择驾驶模式
He can do anything. Right, select drive.
对吧 打给老二
There you go. Call Bell-end.
Bell-end 有丁日之意
看 他拿起了手机 开始拨号
Now, he picks up the phone, he does all the dialling.
我的手还在方向盘上 多安全
My hands are on the wheel, I'm safe.
他帮我放在耳边 这是免提的
He holds it next to my ear so it's hands-free.
老二是谁
Who's Bell-end?
-怎么  -我不想和你说话
- What? - I don't want to talk to you.
挂断电话
End call!
好吧
All right, then.
殴打驾驶员
Punch driver.
殴打... 没用啊
Punch... It doesn't work.
他只听我的指令 这才是神作
He won't respond to you, only me. That's the genius.
还有更棒的 下车
And it gets better. Get out, OK.
他会锁门
He locks the doors.
等我回来 他又打开
And then he opens them when I get back
我就不用随身带钥匙了
so I don't have to have any keys with me,
牛仔裤的线条也不会变形
which would spoil the line of my jean trouser.
让我再梳理一遍
Let me just re-cap this, OK.
在惠特比 你用一位罗马尼亚人
So in Whitby you turned a Romanian man
-造出无人驾驶汽车  -没错
- into a self-driving car. - Yes, I did.
你用我当人肉倒车雷达
You turned me into a parking sensor.
现在 你用一个保加利亚人做语音控制系统
And now you've turned a Bulgarian man into a voice-control system.
-没错  -不言而喻 你的所作所为
- Yes. - There's a theme establishing itself here,
说明你脑子有洞
with your inventions, and it is that you're a moron.
等等 且听我道来
A-ha. OK. Watch this.
现在宝马7系
You know, in a modern BMW 7 Series,
在驾驶过程中
you have back seats that massage you
-可以使用按摩座椅  -是
- as you drive along, yeah? - Yes.
看我的设计 简直天才
What I've done in here... is just genius.
我把座椅中间都挖空了
I have scooped out the middle of that back seat, OK?
可以放一个短芬
And then you can fit it with a Dwan Fen.
-短芬是什么  -她在这呢
- What's a Dwan Fen? - She's here.
她是泰国人
She's from Thailand.
我不知道大家在笑什么
I don't know why people are laughing at this.
她和座椅完美融合了
She now blends perfectly with the seat, OK?
她就是座椅
She is the seat.
所以我只要这样坐上去
So I step in...like so.
我就可以在行进途中 享受按摩了
And then...I get a massage as I drive along.
詹姆斯 他坐在一个泰国女人身上呢
James, James...he's sitting on a Thai woman now.
我知道 快回来 我们继续
I know. Come back over here, and we'll move it on.
回到刚刚的玛莎拉蒂短片中
We'll go back to the Maserati film.
迄今为止 我们能肯定的是
Now, so far we have established
虽然我的胳膊断了
that I've broken my arm,
但是车却依然运行良好
but that the cars are working really rather well.
没错 在多维尔小镇休息一夜后
Yes! And we rejoin the action
我们继续上路
after a night in a town called Deauville,
而杰里米突发奇想
where Jeremy had, for reasons known only to himself,
打算重拍
decided to re-enact
80年代著名的大众高尔夫广告
the famous VW Golf advert from the '80s.
这个男人押了100万在黑色上
This is the man who put a million on black
结果开出了红色
and it came up red.
这个男人娶了一位性感猫女郎
This is the man who married a sex kitten,
结果变成老猫
just as she turned into a cat.
这个男人去淘金
This is the man who moved into gold,
结果功败垂成
just as the clever money moved out.
这个男人 开玛莎拉蒂
This is the man who drives a Maserati.
点火啊 你个死混蛋
Start, you vicious bastard!
当然 玛莎拉蒂最终还是启动了
Of course, being a Maserati, it did eventually begin.
所以给詹姆斯的方向盘装了个小玩意后
So we then fitted James's wheel with a new knob...
我们决定去沙滩上兜兜风
and decided to go and play on the beach.
在法国南部的沙滩上
You really would have trouble doing this
可干不了这事
on a beach in the south of France
因为那里全是
because the whole thing would be covered
想晒黑自己整容脸的人
in people turning their plastic surgery brown.
在海水中驰骋
In the sea!
因为玛莎拉蒂的抗锈做的极好
You can take a Maserati in the sea...
所以你能将它带入海中
because the rust-proofing is so good.
之后 我们一边散步欣赏风景
After that, we enjoyed a picturesque walk
一边进行哲学辩论
and a philosophical debate.
有比其他男人给你背上抹防晒
Is there anything on earth which is worse
更糟的事吗
than having another man put sun cream on your back?
我从未体验过
I've never experienced that.
然后我们运动了一番
And then we played some sport.
在法国南部的沙滩上
Penalty shoot-out
开玛莎拉蒂进行点球大战
in Maseratis on a beach in northern France.
球炸了后
With our ball gone,
我们回到了诺曼底之旅
we continued on our tour of Normandy,
而体弱多病的同事却一直在呻吟
with our badly-built colleague moaning constantly.
谁把船长换成了一个老太太
Has he been swapped for an old lady?
他一直是个老太太
He's always been an old lady.
他生下来就是个老太太
He was born an old lady!
恭喜你 梅夫人 您生了个老太太
"Congratulations, Mrs May. It's an old lady!"
夜色降临时 我们到达了翁弗勒尔古镇
As darkness fell, we reached the ancient town of Honfleur,
决定在此留宿一夜
where we decided to spend the night.
但 为了抵达酒店
Unfortunately, to reach our hotel,
我们得在迷宫般的
we had to navigate through a maze
中世纪狭窄街道中行驶
of tiny, medieval streets.
不好意思 抱歉
Pardon. Sorry.
这太窄了 不是吗
This is narrow. Isn't it narrow?
别啊
No.
以前没有动力转向的时候
How did people manage in this town in the olden days
这里的人都怎么开车的
when nobody had power steering?
哦不
Oh, no.
这该怎么办
I do that how?
哦我的天哪
Oh, my God.
我彻底卡住了
I'm totally stuck.
都是石子路
Ow, ow, ow, ow. Cobbles.
我的神啊
God almighty.
我不确定这可行
I'm not sure that's possible.
卧了个…那是
Oh, for... Is that...?
你挡道了
You're in the way.
我这边是单行道
It's a one-way street my way.
它的确是单行道
It's a one-way street, yes.
所以我和别的车
That's why me and the other cars
都在往这方向开
are all coming this way.
别让我用这破转向再退回去
Please don't make me back up with this steering.
来吧 就当锻炼了
Come on, it's a workout.
哈蒙德 我要杀了你
Hammond, I am gonna kill you.
请稍等
Moment, s'il vous plaît.
我的朋友
他开车子
像大猩猩一样
你要的火腿
Vous devrez...le jambon
要开走 这里堵了
前面左转
我们就搞定啦
我们就是蘑菇了
等杰里米移开了 我也可以继续了
With Jeremy out of the way, I could move on.
但是接着
But then...
哈蒙德 那个开黄灯过来的是你吗
Hammond, is that you with yellow lights coming up here?
-我的天 -这真不走运
- Oh, my God. - That's a bit of bad luck.
你得倒车了 对吧
You're going to have to reverse up there, aren't you?
我不能 因为这里窄得离谱
I can't back up because it's preposterously narrow
而且我没法转头看后面
and I can't swivel my head round to look behind me.
你说该咋办
So now what?
好吧 我在这单行道上
Well, I'm going the right way
开的是正确的方向
down the one-way street,
所以路权归我
so I have right of way.
不好意思哈蒙德 你要帮我指挥一下
Sorry, Hammond, you'll have to direct me a bit.
-右一点 -我的右还是你的右
- Right a bit. - My right or your right?
好吧 我的右 也就是你的左
Well, my right. Which is your left
但是你在倒车
but you're steering in reverse.
停在那里 我要往左了
Hold it there and I'll go left.
你的左还是我的左
Your left or my left?
我看的是你的右边 我的左边
Your right, my left as I'm looking.
而你所看的你的右边 也就是你的右边
And your right as you're looking, i.e. your right.
我找到宾馆了
I had found the hotel,
但是显然我的同事们还要一会
but clearly my colleagues were going to be a while.
当你说我的左边 你是指我的左边吗
When you say my left, do you mean my left
是我要去的这个方向
if I'm facing the way I'm going
还是我面朝的方向
or facing the way I'm facing?
问的好
Good point.
你的左边还是我的右边
Your left is still my right.
但是你在倒车 就这么开
But you're going backwards. Just drive backwards!
我要去宾馆了但是我要把这个开着
I'm going to the hotel now but I'll leave this on
你能实时监听他们的动向
so you can stay in tune with what they're doing.
我才不相信我开错路
I don't believe I've come the wrong way
到了一条单行道上 我知道的
down a one-way street. I know.
你在让处境变好还是变差
Are you making your situation better or worse?
更好 更差 更好 更差
Better? Worse? Better? Worse?
当理查德和船长终于和我一起
When Richard and James did finally join me,
我们在晚餐时反思了一下
we reflected over dinner
我们在法国北部的这些时间
about our time in the north of France.
这是段极好的旅程
It's been just a tremendous journey.
我们外面有三辆玛莎拉蒂 开了三天
We've had three Maseratis out here for three days
却不能开个过瘾
and we've only had one minor fire.
我能说 而且很认真的说
Can I just say, and I'm being absolutely honest here,
我爱我的玛莎拉蒂
I love my Maserati.
-我彻底迷上了它 -是的
- I've totally fallen for it. - Yes.
我很喜欢我的车
I really like mine.
没有车的声浪更动听
No car makes a better noise.
这是最动听的2.0升发动机
No two-litre car makes a better noise than that.
我比启程的时候更爱它
I love it more now than when I started.
我绝对想把它留下
I definitely want to keep mine.
我想知道用两只手开会是什么感觉
I want to know what it's like to drive with two arms.
因为我们都太喜欢这些车了
Because we all loved our cars so much,
我觉得应该用一个火辣的高潮
I decided we should end our road trip
来结束这次旅行
with a spicy climax.
我们为什么不比赛谁先开回英国
Why don't we race back to England, OK?
一大早出发 最后一个回到那里的
First thing in the morning. Last one back there...
要把车卖了
has to sell their car.
-噢 这好残忍  -太残酷了
- Ooh, that's cruel. - That's harsh.
这对我不太公平吧 不是吗
It's not entirely fair on me, is it?
为什么不
Hello. Why not?
你自己决定只带一只胳膊来
You chose to come equipped with one arm.
这是你的问题 不是我们的
It's your issue, not ours.
所以我们从这里同时出发
So we set off from here, all at the same time.
任何路线 最后一个
Any route you like. Last one...
回到英国本土的
back on English soil,
要把车卖了
has to sell their car.
我资瓷 来赌一把
I'm up for it. I'll risk it
因为那会让回家的路程变得很刺激
cos that'll make the trip home exciting.
我会做的 最后一个到家
I'll do it. Last one home...
破晓时分
As dawn broke,
我们在宾馆外一字排开
we lined up outside the hotel,
准备出发
ready for the off.
先生们 现在时早上9:56分
Gentlemen, it's ten to four in the morning.
我们走吧
Let's do this.
三 二 一 开始
In three, two, one... Begin!
冲啊
Blast!
走
Come on!
不 不
No! No!
不惜任何代价 我要赢
At all costs, I am winning this.
这是辆典型的意大利车
This is typical. Typical of Italian cars.
它等到你最需要它的时候
They wait until you really need them,
然后才出差错
and then they go wrong.
"哦亲爱的 我快生啦 你快点"
“Oh, darling, darling, I'm in labour! Quickly!"
我开着玛莎拉蒂在路上呢
"Yes, I'm on my way in my Maserati."
好的 走这边
Right. Up here.
这里很熟悉 不是好兆头
Some of this is familiar, which is bad.
哦不 现在别迷路啊
Oh, no, not lost now.
我又一次哄开心我的车
Once again, I'd managed to coax my car
让它正常工作
into some kind of life
我出发了
and I was on my way.
驶出镇子
So, straight out of town.
听着还行
Sounding healthy.
在最高20km/h的时速下
With a top speed of about 12,
前往勒阿弗尔的渡船码头
I was headed for the ferry port of Le Havre.
问题是 按理说
The trouble is that logically,
他们两人也会如此
the others would be doing the same thing.
车啊 清清你的嗓子 求你了
Car, clear your throat, please.
我出来了
I'm out!
好的 英国我来了
Right, England, here I come.
求你了 清清嗓子吧
Clear your throat, car! Clear it!
不然我们就要垫底了
Or we shall be last.
我就得把你卖了 而且我绝对不会卖给好人
And then I shall have to sell you, and I won't sell you to someone nice.
你知道有人会艹车
You know that man who has sex with his cars
还会把照片发到网上
and then puts pictures of it on the internet?
我要把你卖给他
I'm going to sell you to him
除非你走起来 现在 走啊
unless you get going. Now, come on!
-等等 -不
- Hang on a minute. - No!
不不不
No, no, no, no!
路况真棒
Big road. Yes!
与此同时
James, meanwhile,
船长还在后面闲逛
was dawdling along at the back.
他似乎毫不在乎这事
Yet he seemed strangely unconcerned about this.
从表面上看 这不太算是一场比赛
On the face of it, viewers, this isn't much of a race,
因为我的车是最慢的 我们已经知道了
because I've got the slowest car, we already know that.
我只能用一只胳膊
I only have the use of one arm
而且我还得握着
and I'm steering
方向盘上的尖叫蛙来转向
with a squeaky frog bolted to the wheel.
然而 并没有那么简单
However, it's not that simple.
事实上
In fact,
我相信我会是第一
I believe I will be first.
在后的将要在前
Because he who is last shall be first.
出自马太福音19章30节
"然而有许多在前的将要在后，在后的将要在前"
圣经记载说
As we know.
现在上高速公路
Coming up now to the motorway.
加油啊 拜托
Come on, car. Please!
我已经成功开上匝道了
It's made it up the slip road.
你可曾见过比这辆
Have you ever known a car with more spirit
华丽的玛莎拉蒂更有个性的车
than this magnificent Maserati?
然而 匝道的坡度比起前方的挑战
However, the gradient on the slip road was nothing
根本算不上什么
compared to what lay ahead.
此为诺曼底大桥
哦 我的姑奶奶啊
Oh, my giddy aunt.
港口在哪里
Port, where is it?
如果我第一个到那里 我得等渡轮
If I get there first, I've got to wait for the ferry.
他们就会赶上我 但是我在队伍前面
They could catch up, but I'll be ahead in the queue.
第一个上船的人也第一个下船
Whoever gets on the boat first gets off the boat first,
这是一定的
and you can't change that.
如果他们先上船
First on the boat is first off the boat.
他们就赢了
They win.
好的 冷静点 杰里米
Right, calm, Jeremy, calm.
你在高速公路上
You're on a motorway.
在一座大桥上
On an enormous bridge,
被很多重卡包围
surrounded by many heavy lorries.
哦不
Oh, no.
我可以听到排气在噼啪响
I can hear the exhaust spluttering.
烟 冒出了好多烟
Smoke. A lot of smoke now.
拜托 振作点
Please! Please work!
万幸 我到了桥顶
Mercifully, I reach the top of the bridge.
但是
But then...
它挂了
It's dead.
卧槽 刹车失灵了
Shit, I've lost braking. I have lost braking.
真他妈的 手刹也不行了
Bloody hell. Handbrake not working, either.
我的刹车完全失灵了
I've lost all brakes.
我现在别无选择
There was only one thing for it.
我没有刹车
I have no brakes!
你刚撞了我们的车
You've just hit our car!
我刹车坏了
I haven't got any brakes!
被当成刹车来用
They're not pleased
他们似乎不太高兴
about being used as a brake.
顺便一提 在法国公路上
This is totally illegal, by the way,
这是完全违法的
on a French motorway.
好的 我没有刹车
Right, so I've no brakes
没有动力
and no engine.
杰里米 好好想想
Think, Jeremy, think.
港口 你好
Port. Yes, hello.
对杰里米的状况毫不知情
Unaware of Jeremy's problems,
我继续前行
I was keeping the hammer down.
度假者
Holiday-makers!
我恨度假者
I hate holiday-makers!
卡车
Trucks.
我要超过所有的卡车
I'm going to get caught up with all the trucks.
与此同时 回到船长那边
Meanwhile, back in the land of Captain Cryptic...
你知道吗 我很享受这个过程
Do you know, I'm so relaxed about this,
我想 再过一会
I think, in a short while,
我可能会停下来喝一杯咖啡
I might stop for a pleasant coffee
读读报纸
and a read of the newspaper.
我在赶时间 抱歉了伙计
Not got time for you, mate. I'm sorry.
有车
Car! Car!
天啊 又一个环岛
Oh, God. Another roundabout.
好像我在市中心一样
It's like I'm in the middle of bloody town.
我得自己找条路
I need to find my own route.
这里肯定有小路能穿出去
There must be sneaky ways through.
会好的 会好的
This could be good. This could be good.
走这边
Down there.
噢
Oh!
死胡同
Dead end.
不是这边 见鬼了
Not that way. Bloody hell.
我抄近路的计划并没奏效
My shortcut wasn't going well.
他们在哪儿 更重要的我在哪儿
Where are they and more importantly where am I?
这招走错了 我搞砸了
This was a mistake. This is making things worse.
这只是浪费时间
It's just costing time.
事实证明
And, as it turned out,
我现在最大的敌人就是时间
time was something I didn't have.
我现在只剩一个涡轮了
I am now down to one turbo charger,
但我又回到了比赛里
but I'm back in the race.
是的 我在开一台雷诺DCI 120拖车
Yes, I'm at the wheel of a Renault DCI 120 tow truck.
更重要的是 我决定
And what's more, I've decided
飞奔至港口
to head for the port as the crow flies.
太棒了
Oh, yes!
噢天啊 不
Oh, God, no!
这边好像对了
This looks good.
没错 渡轮码头
Yes. Ferry terminal.
这就对了
This is all correct.
那是杰里米
That is Jeremy!
那是哈蒙德
There's Hammond!
他在干什么
What is he doing?
干掉他
Kill him!
我必须要赢
I have to win. I have to win.
有个环岛 哦 天啊 真的么
A roundabout. Oh, bloody hell. Really?
问题是 勒阿弗尔的码头太大了
The problem was that the port of Le Havre is so vast
又复杂 很容易迷路
and so complex, it was very easy to get lost.
谁都有可能赢
This was still anyone's race.
哈蒙德在哪里 梅在哪里
Where is Hammond? Where is May?
船在哪里
Where is the boat?
加油啊
Come on, come on, come on.
这条路不对 这条路不对
This is wrong. This is wrong.
应该是沿着这条路走
It's got to be down here.
是的
Yes!
刚才油门被地毯卡住了吗
Did I have some carpet stuck under the throttle?
我的DCI 120简直快得飞起啊
Cos my DCI 120's going like a bastard!
啊 没错 就是这里
Yes! This looks good. This is the place.
好货车 乖货车 船就在那里
Good van. Good van. The boat is there.
哈蒙德已经到了 梅到了吗
There is Richard Hammond. Is James May here?
不 他没到
No, he is not!
他没到
He is not.
好棒
Yes!
哈哈 看到梅了吗
Ha-ha! No May?
不 他们不可能看见我
No, and there wouldn't be,
因为我在港口的另一边
because I was in another part of the port
我有自己的计划
with my own travel plans.
昨晚 在他们两个上床之后
Last night, after the other two had gone to bed,
我预定了一艘我们公司的游艇
I arranged for our company yacht
让它在码头等我
to be waiting for me in the harbour.
看 它在那儿
And there it is!
我只要开过去 跳上船
I simply drive up, hop aboard,
然后就可以上路了
and then we'll be on our way.
-很遗憾 他活了下来 -等一下
- He lived, annoyingly. - Hold on, hold on.
等一下 哈蒙德
Hold on. Hammond.
你得解释下这个
I need to ask you about this.
为什么你要在我的车上贴一个"Déshabille"
Why did you stick "Déshabille"on my car?
因为你当时残疾了啊
Because you were disabled.
Déshabille的意思是一丝不挂 你个蠢货
Déshabille means undressed, you moron!
我们就不要纠结于
Let's not get bogged down
噢我不会说法语 之类的话了
with "Ooh, can't speak French."
言归正传 詹姆斯梅
Let's get to the point which is, James May,
你输了 还把公司的游艇撞坏了
you lost and you broke the company yacht.
-是的 -等等
- You did. - Hang on a minute.
我的车比你们的离英国更近
My car got closer to England than yours did.
没错 但是我觉得
Yes, but the other thing it got closest to
它离海底更近吧
was the bottom of the sea.
你们说那些都没用
All of that is irrelevant
因为我的车才是最好的
because my car was the best,
整段旅程它都没坏
cos it didn't go wrong at all.
我的车也极为可靠
Mine was perfectly reliable.
嗯 我的车就像詹姆斯的胳膊一样靠谱
Mm-hm. Mine was as reliable as James's arms.
最离奇的是 没人能弄清楚
And the extraordinary thing is, no-one can work out
那辆车到底哪里有问题
what was wrong with it.
它从拖车上掉下去了
It fell off the back of a lorry.
不 没人能搞清楚它到底哪儿坏了
No- one can work out what fault it had
以至于要上拖车
that caused it to be on the lorry in the first place.
现在这段都拍完了9个月了
And even nine months down the line,
两位专业的玛莎拉蒂技师被彻底难住了
two trained Maserati mechanics are totally stumped.
这真是个令人难以理解问题
It is an unfathomable fault.
是啊 所以从法国北部的测试
Yeah, so what we can conclude
我们得出如下结论
from our exhaustive testing in the north of France
如果你买了一台二手玛莎拉蒂
is that if you buy a used Maserati,
有66%的概率能碰到台正常运转的
you have a 66% chance of it working.
听起来还不错嘛
They're not bad odds.
你要是在做眼科手术前
You wouldn't say that
听到这个成功率 你肯定不会这么说
if you were having an eye operation.
是啊 随着这个失望的消息 节目也该结束了
Exactly. And on that terrible disappointment, it's time to end.
感谢各位的收看 晚安
Thank you so much for watching. Good night!